<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The blessednes of Brytaine, or A celebration of the Queenes holyday Wherein is briefly discoursed the most happy regiment of her Highnes. Newly set foorth vvith a nevv addition containing the late accidents and occurrents of this yeere 88. being the thirtieth of hir Maiesties raigne. By M. Kyffin. Published with authoritie.</title>
            <author>Kyffin, Maurice, d. 1599.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1588</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 47 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 17 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A04955</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 15097</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S108160</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843844</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843844</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8603</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A04955)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8603)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 254:02)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The blessednes of Brytaine, or A celebration of the Queenes holyday Wherein is briefly discoursed the most happy regiment of her Highnes. Newly set foorth vvith a nevv addition containing the late accidents and occurrents of this yeere 88. being the thirtieth of hir Maiesties raigne. By M. Kyffin. Published with authoritie.</title>
                  <author>Kyffin, Maurice, d. 1599.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[32] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by [John Windet for] Iohn VVolfe,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1588.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>In verse.</note>
                  <note>Actual printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Henry E. Huntington Library and Art Gallery.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Elizabeth --  I, --  Queen of England, 1533-1603 --  Poetry --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-08</date>
            <label>Lauren Proux</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-09</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:1"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:1"/>
                  <p>THE BLESSEDNES OF <hi>BRYTAINE, OR</hi> A Celebration of the Queenes Holyday.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Wherein is briefly diſcourſed the most happy</hi> Regiment of her Highnes.</p>
                  <p>Newly ſet foorth vvith a Nevv <hi>Addition Containing the late Accidents and Occur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents</hi> of this yeere 88. being the <hi>Thirtieth</hi> of hir Maieſties Raigne.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By M. Kyffin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1.</hi> Pet. <hi>2.17.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <p>Deum timete: Regem Honorate.</p>
                  </q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>1. Tim. 2.2.</bibl>
                     <p>Fiant preces pro Regibus &amp; Principibus, vt tranquillam &amp; quietam vitam degamus cum omni pietate &amp; honeſtate.</p>
                  </q>
                  <p>Publiſhed with Authoritie.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON Printed by John VVolfe.</hi> 1588.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:2"/>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:2"/>
                  <head>TO THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable Sir Robert Devreux Knight, Erle <hi>of Eſſex and Ewe, Vicount Hereford, and Bourgchier,</hi> Lord Ferrers of Chartleigh, Bourgchier and Lovain, and Maiſter of her Maieſties Horſe.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE faythfull loue, and duetie, (Right honorable) long ſince deſeruedly born, by my deceaſed Father, both to your lordſhips Noble Graundfather, and likewiſe to the famous and woorthie Erle your Father, (vnto whom for diuers reſpects, hee was much bounden being aliue, and being dead, left the like Bond of dutie, in vs his Children towards your Lordſhip) hath the more emboldened me, (preſuming on your Lordſhips great Courteſies) to publiſh under your fauorable protecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, theſe my vnpoliſhed verſes, of hir Maieſties: wherein, though I haue but ſhowen my leaden skill, in a <hi>Golden Cauſe,</hi> yet hath the ſame pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeded from ſuch ardent deſire, and deuotion in mee, as thereby it may ſeeme, in ſome meane, to merite Tolleration, eſpecially, ſith it carrieth a dutifull remembrance, of hir Maiesties most proſperous and <hi>peacea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble</hi> raigne ouer vs: which hauing run the full, and Bleſſed Courſe, of <hi>Nyne and Twenty yeeres;</hi> doth now, begin the <hi>Thirtieth,</hi> to the great ioy, and inſpeakeable comfort of this hir royall Kingdome; In reuerend regard whereof, this poore Poem is most chiefly intended: I humbly therefore, preſent it to the Courteous acceptation of your most Honorable Lordſhip: Whom I beſeech the <hi>Higheſt</hi> to bleſſe, and enriche, with increaſe of all perfect Honour, long life, and euer during felicitie.</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Moſt humble at your good Lordſhips commandment. M. K.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
               <div type="to_the_reader">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:3"/>
                  <opener>
                     <signed>D. P.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <head>To the Reader.</head>
                  <l>TWo things make blisfull Realmes, <hi>Religion</hi> pure and <hi>Peace:</hi>
                  </l>
                  <l>Which <hi>Two</hi> our <hi>England</hi> hath enioyd, long time with large increaſe.</l>
                  <l>The God of peace be praiſd, who graunts our Birth and Being.</l>
                  <l>In this ſame <hi>Realme,</hi> with this <hi>Rare Prince,</hi> theſe <hi>gladſome Seaſons</hi> ſeeing.</l>
                  <l>And pray wee God likewiſe, this State ſtill to defend:</l>
                  <l>Preſeruing it in perfect Peace, til that the worlde take end.</l>
                  <l>The Author of this booke, deſerues a during fame,</l>
                  <l>Who choſe a good Grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d for his work, &amp; wrought well on the ſame.</l>
               </div>
               <div type="praise">
                  <opener>
                     <signed>T. LL.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <head>In praiſe of this booke, and the Author.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>WHo liſt to ſee her Noble deeds diſplaid,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe golden gifts, eche creature doth adore,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Vertues Rare, haue hauty hearts diſmaid,</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Name, and Fame, encreaſeth more and more:</l>
                     <l>Let them peruſe this Poem, with Aduiſe,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>Kyffins</hi> pen, put down in perfect wiſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A work of woorth, beſeeming well his Arte,</l>
                     <l>So fitly framd, and fraught with tryed Truthe,</l>
                     <l>As may Reioyce, eche loyall ſubiects heart,</l>
                     <l>To heare, and ſee; which hidden had bin Ruthe.</l>
                     <l>Our Queenes long Raigne, to our ſtill during ioy,</l>
                     <l>The King of Kings, preſerue free from Annoy.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="praise">
                  <opener>
                     <signed>I. H.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <head>In commendation of this worke, and the writer.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>THe Perſian <hi>Cyrus, Xenophons</hi> penne, <hi>Achilles, Homersfound:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>King <hi>Alexanders</hi> valure great, did <hi>Curtius</hi> ſtile reſound,</l>
                     <l>Their worthie fame, thoſe worthie wittes, to skies aloft doo ſend,</l>
                     <l>Thoſe worthie wits, cake by their fame themſelues to fame commend.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Though skilfull Muſes notes come ſhort to ſound this Princeſſe prayſe,</l>
                     <l>Her Princely gifts, her Iuſtice mylde, her Peacefull laſting dayes:</l>
                     <l>Yet <hi>Kyffins</hi> Muſe in ſtately ſtile, hath ſhot: ſo neare the ſame.</l>
                     <l>That by reſounding worthie praiſe, himſelfe deſerueth fame.</l>
                  </lg>
               </div>
               <div type="praise">
                  <opener>
                     <signed>R. Cooke.</signed>
                  </opener>
                  <head>In commendation of his friend M. Kyffin.</head>
                  <l>THe frutefull Muſes ſeeme, to haue conſpird, with full aſſent,</l>
                  <l>Vplifting <hi>Kyffins</hi> lore, with weightie woords to work Content:</l>
                  <l>The ſubiect of his Verſe, is ſacred, firme, and full of grace,</l>
                  <l>Whereon his Web is wrought, whoſe learned skill, none can deface,</l>
                  <l>
                     <hi>Momus</hi> the carping God, to Cauill heere can finde no cauſe,</l>
                  <l>And <hi>Zoylus</hi> ſpitefull wretch, hath heere wherewith to ſtop his iawes.</l>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:3"/>
                  <head>THE BLESSEDNES OF BRYTAINE.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>PEarce <hi>Clio Muſe,</hi> my weake, vnwoorthie wit:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Caliope,</hi> ſet foorth my ſtile with ſtrength,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nfold her <hi>Fame</hi> (with words foorth ſounding fit,)</l>
                     <l>Whom <hi>Kings</hi> adore, and <hi>Lords</hi> in worldly length:</l>
                     <l>Whoſe Sacred Hands the <hi>Stately Scepters</hi> hold,</l>
                     <l>And Royall, Rules her Realmes in <hi>Crowned gold.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A <hi>Monarch Maiden Queene</hi> adorned rare,</l>
                     <l>VVith Regall Heauenly dowres, of diuers kinde:</l>
                     <l>In whom, who liſt <hi>dame Natures Woorkes</hi> compare,</l>
                     <l>VVith thoſe rich <hi>Thewes,</hi> &amp; <hi>Vertues</hi> of her Minde,</l>
                     <l>Shall much admire, at ſuch a <hi>Myrrour</hi> ſheene,</l>
                     <l>At ſuch a <hi>Prince,</hi> at ſuch a <hi>Peereles Queene.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:4"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Starre</hi> of VVomen Sex, <hi>Graue Wiſdoms ſtore:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Sententious, ſpeaking Tongs in filed phraze,</l>
                     <l>Profoundly learnd, and Perfect in eche Lore,</l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Fame,</hi> no Rav'ning Time ſhall euer Raze:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Hater</hi> of <hi>Wrong, high Refuge</hi> eke for <hi>Right,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Concord,</hi> and <hi>Peace,</hi> continuing by her Might.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Beſides that ſuch maner of Reciting ſtrange and Hetheniſh Names, were here altoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nient. The author doth alſo of very purpoſe, ſomewhat ſhun that beaten high way, to fill paper with peſtring Names of fained Gods, Goddeſſes: Nymphs, Per<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſians, Greci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Romans, &amp;c. Being a thing of ſome ſom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times vſed, too, too much &amp; to litle effect.</note>VVhat ſhould J <hi>Nymphs,</hi> or <hi>Goddeſſes</hi> Recount?</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Aegypt Queenes,</hi> or <hi>Romane Ladies</hi> name?</l>
                     <l>Sith as Supreme, <hi>our Sov'raigne</hi> dooth ſurmount,</l>
                     <l>In choice of <hi>Good,</hi> the cheefe of all thoſe ſame?</l>
                     <l>For to compare the <hi>Great,</hi> with ſimple <hi>ſmall,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Is thereby, not to praiſe the <hi>BEST</hi> at all.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> Large Light of <hi>Sov'raigne Seat,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhoſe <hi>Iuſtice, Prudence, Temprance, Fortitude,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Ingrafted yong, are grown foorth ſpreading Great,</l>
                     <l>Throughout the world, mong Nations wiſe &amp; rude:</l>
                     <l>No land, but laudes this <hi>right Reſplendant Roſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Tutor</hi> to <hi>Frends,</hi> and <hi>Terror</hi> vnto <hi>Foes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:4"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As <hi>Shining Sunne</hi> recleeres the darkned Skye,<note place="margin">The reeſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhing of the Goſpell, by her Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie, a work of ineſtima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble worth, e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerlaſtingly famous for e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer and euer. <hi>Primaria Principis Curia, Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gio.</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>. 13. Aſa. 2. par. 14 Icho. 2. P. 17 Ioaſh. 2. p. 23 Ioſias, 2. Reg. 22. Hez. 2. p. 29.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And foorth recalles eche thing, from ſhiv'ring Shrowds,</l>
                     <l>So hath our <hi>Second Sunne,</hi> both farre and nye,</l>
                     <l>By brightning Beames, <hi>outcleerd erronious Clouds:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A pow'rfull Prop of <hi>Chriſtes Euangell</hi> pure,</l>
                     <l>On whoſe Support, it reſts Repoſed ſure.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our <hi>Currant Coyne,</hi> was Mettall baſe and meane,<note place="margin">Argentum tuu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Scoria. <hi>Iſaiah. 1.22.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Till her moſt princely <hi>Grace,</hi> the ſame put out,</l>
                     <l>By perfect Gold, and pured Siluer cleane,<note place="margin">Baſe Coynes aboliſhed by her highnes.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which paſſe for co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon Coynes, her Realms throughout.</l>
                     <l>A Deede, deſeruing her Perpetuall Praiſe,</l>
                     <l>And Publik Profit, to this Land alwaies.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ad hereto <hi>Armour,</hi> and <hi>Artillerie,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>The royal in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mour, &amp; Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tillery, by her Maieſtie for the defence of the Realm.</hi> Foelix eſt ea Reſp. quae te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pore pacis, Bella tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctat. Laur. Grimal. de optimo Sena<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tore. fol. 71.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of her moſt Royall Charges cheefely found;</l>
                     <l>As ſtore of <hi>Arming ſteele</hi> defenſiuely,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Roring Gunnes,</hi> far rendring fired ſound;</l>
                     <l>A furd'ring Strength for <hi>Peace,</hi> and ſafe Repoſe:</l>
                     <l>And Meanes, reſisting Rage, of <hi>Warring foes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:5"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>J may not heere omit in Silent ſorte,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>The incompa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rable Nauie. Royall, built &amp; maintained by her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtie.</hi> Pericles A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then, ait: V<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>na<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pecuniae para<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dae rati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onem puta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam, Naues qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plurimas ha bere, alias ve<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ro extra eam rationes, nul lius mome<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ti exiſtima<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>das.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Her <hi>Royall Ships</hi> ſtrong wrought for <hi>ſtearnfull war,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>(<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hereof all worldly Realmes doe raiſe Report)</l>
                     <l>Through raging Seas diſcouering Regions farre:</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Scowre-ſea Nauy</hi> all bright &amp; brauely burniſht,</l>
                     <l>Foorth ſpowting fire, faire, huge, and fully furniſht.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hen flooriſht <hi>Learning</hi> to ſuch <hi>Type of hight?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Or <hi>purefull Preaching,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Plentifull ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe of Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on in al Kinde of learning, &amp; right whol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome lawes, enioyed by her Maieſties moſtgratious meanes.</note> when had It more place?</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hen was <hi>Gods worde</hi> ſo knowne to euery wight,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hich heretofore, did ſuffer ſuch Deface?</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hen raignd <hi>Religion</hi> ſo deuoide of eryme?</l>
                     <l>Or Rightfull <hi>Lawes,</hi> as in her Royall time?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The Realme wonderfully enriched with Gold &amp; Siluer. The earth moſt abundantly bleſſed with fertility. And euery man quietly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ioying his owne, vnder her highnes proſperous gouernment.</note>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hen was this Realme ſo rich of glittring <hi>Gold,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of <hi>plated Siluer, pearle,</hi> and <hi>precious ſtones?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hen was more <hi>Tillage</hi> on this fertile Mold?</l>
                     <l>Or more riche streaming Graces growne at ones?</l>
                     <l>Or more <hi>Concordant life,</hi> in Country and Towne,</l>
                     <l>Then ſince her <hi>Regall Highnes came to Crowne?</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:5"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The vigilant Care and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſant trauel of her Maie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſties moſt ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norable pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Councell.</note>
                        <hi>Her ſacred Senate</hi> by their graue foreſight,</l>
                     <l>Prouide for <hi>Publik Good</hi> and <hi>Ev'ls</hi> preuent,</l>
                     <l>Conſeruing <hi>Common weale,</hi> from Perils plight,</l>
                     <l>In Rightfull Ruling, Concord, &amp; Concent:</l>
                     <l>A <hi>Senate</hi> well beſitting ſuch a Charge;</l>
                     <l>Prudent, &amp; prompt in Lore and Wiſdome large.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The moſt bleſſed and peaceable ſtate of her Maieſties ſub<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>iects in com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pariſon of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Nations round about them. Strangers gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ciouſly recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued by hir Highnes. within hir own king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom.</note>From Wrathfull <hi>Warre,</hi> her People rest in <hi>Peace:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>From <hi>waſting Woes,</hi> her Subiects liue Secure:</l>
                     <l>And yet our Neighbour Nations Warres not ceaſe,</l>
                     <l>Their dire diſtreſſe, and wailfull Woes ſtill dure;</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Moſt of Might,</hi> eke makes her Realm a towr</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Strangers</hi> to ſhield, from many a balefull Showr.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A <hi>Mightie Queene,</hi> pure with Compaſsion preſt,<note place="margin">
                           <hi>Her Maieſties gratious aidg vnto hir di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtreſſed neigh<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>bors abroad.</hi> Regia (crede<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>mthi) res eſt ſuccurrere lapſis, Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nit vt tante quantus es<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ipſe viro. Ouid. lib. 2. de Pon.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Rendring Reliefe, to Neighbour freends forlorn:</l>
                     <l>Her helping Hand, holds vp the weake diſtreſt,</l>
                     <l>And hath the haughtie, dreadfull, oft downborn:</l>
                     <l>VVhereof Records, full rife remaining ſtore,</l>
                     <l>Note <hi>Scotland,</hi>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Low Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tries.</note> Belgia, and many places more.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:6"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>Her Highnes bountifull li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitie. Her Mercy towardes of fenders.</hi> Imperia du<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> bus potiſsimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> contine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tur, Nempe, Proemio &amp; Paena, teſte Solone. Iuſticia ſine Miſericor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dia Crudelitas. Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricordia ſine Iuſtitia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuitas.</note>
                        <hi>Lib'rall Rewarder</hi> of <hi>Heroicall</hi> Acts;</l>
                     <l>Ritch in Reward, large giuing Gwerdons great;</l>
                     <l>Prone eke to pardon, many offending facts,</l>
                     <l>Yea though the ſame, concern her <hi>Regall Seate;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rigor</hi> of <hi>Iuſtice,</hi> in Reuenging Lawes,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Mylde</hi> by her <hi>Mercy,</hi> wreaks not eche Cauſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A Bleſſed Branch of <hi>Brutus</hi> Royall Race;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Her Maieſtie Princeſſe of Wales, wher the Inhabi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tants enioy Gods woord in their own language, through the meere grace and goodnes of hirhigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</note>To <hi>Brytiſh wightes</hi> a Blisfull worldly ioy,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Puiſſant Princeſſe</hi> of Their Natiue place,</l>
                     <l>To ſhield their Earthly liues from all annoy:</l>
                     <l>And to their Sickly Soules, a Sov'raigne Leche,</l>
                     <l>Granting <hi>Chriſts Goſpel,</hi> in their Country ſpeche.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Princely Poſſeſſor</hi> of this Realme full Right,</l>
                     <l>And <hi>Heire apparant</hi> to the <hi>Heav'nly Crowne:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Aſsign'd to ſerue <hi>Gods Truth,</hi> with Maine &amp; Might</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-raiſing <hi>Vertue; Vice</hi> depreſsing downe:</l>
                     <l>Frutefull in <hi>Faith,</hi> though fruteleſſe, wanting feere:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Such</hi> brings ſhe<note n="*" place="margin">A perpetu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al memory of her manifold goodnes, in ſteede of Sounes and daughters. <hi>Praeferre pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>triam liberis Rege<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>decet. Sence in Tr.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Frute,</hi> inſteade of Children heere.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:6"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Omnis laus virtutis in Actione con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſtit. Ariſt.</note>
                        <hi>Such</hi> Rare, Renowmed <hi>Deeds,</hi> our <hi>Queene</hi> hath don</l>
                     <l>And more than my poore powre may well expreſſe:</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Violenta nemo Impe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ria co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuit diu. Sen. in Tr.</note>Long hath her Raigne, this <hi>Glorious Race</hi> foorth run</l>
                     <l>Long may it laſt, foorth bringing frutes no leſſe:</l>
                     <l>Great is the <hi>Good,</hi> thus grown foorth, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>her Grace:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Great good</hi> ſhal grow, through hir like le<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gthned ſpace</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">A reproofe vnto Tray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tors.</note>O wretched Wights, that would this <hi>Queene</hi> enharme,</l>
                     <l>By cloſe contryuing of her Cruell Death;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">They rewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded me Euill for Good: for they haue priuily layde their Net to deſtroy me without cauſe. Pſal. 35.</note>VVhat curſed <hi>Circes,</hi> coulde their mindes ſo charme,</l>
                     <l>As not to recke, to reaue their <hi>Liege</hi> of breath?</l>
                     <l>Fell Raging <hi>Rome,</hi> all this is long of thee,</l>
                     <l>From whom, no Troubling Treaſons, here are free.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Our <hi>kingly Rooted Roſe,</hi> freſh flowring ſtands;</l>
                     <l>Garded by <hi>Gods</hi> great Powre, and Prouidence:</l>
                     <l>Amaſing much, all Traitours trembling hands,</l>
                     <l>VVhich plye to pluck this <hi>Plant</hi> by violence:</l>
                     <l>Yea<note n="*" place="margin">Mag<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>s eſt veritas, &amp; Praualet. <hi>Eſdras. 3. c. 4.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Truthe</hi> downe treading <hi>Treaſon</hi> vnto ſhame,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ictor ſuruiues, by vanquiſhing the ſame.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:7"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thriſe happie <hi>Land,</hi> whoſe Sov'raigne Ladies life,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Lord</hi> enlengthning, ſaues from ſodein haps;</l>
                     <l>Though Ciuile Bronds, and forrain Furies rife,</l>
                     <l>Conioyning erſt, haue threatned <hi>Thunder claps,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet Maugre <hi>Malice,</hi> Foes are put to foyle,<note place="margin">Si Deusno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>biſcum quit contra nos. Pau. 8. Ro.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And ſafe remaines, our <hi>Sov'raigne,</hi> &amp; our <hi>Soyle.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The Angel of the Lord ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rieth about them that feare him, &amp; that put their truſt in him. Pſal. 34. There is no king that can be ſaued by the multitude of an Hoſte. &amp;c. Behold the Eye of the Lord is vpon them that feare him, &amp; that put their truſt in his Mercy. Pſal. 33.</note>Thriſe happy <hi>Queene,</hi> acknown of <hi>God</hi> ſo deere,</l>
                     <l>Gainſt whom, what ſecret Miſcheefs haue bin ſought,</l>
                     <l>But that the ſame, would preſently appeere,</l>
                     <l>By meanes <hi>Miraculous,</hi> as yet vnwrought?</l>
                     <l>A Sured Signe, whom <hi>God</hi> protects to <hi>Ioy,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No <hi>lurking Ev'l,</hi> can thereto worke Annoy.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O <hi>Glorious Ruler</hi> of the gliſtring <hi>Heav'n,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Prolong her Health, with Heaps of happy Yeeres,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The praier &amp; wiſh of all good Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects.</note>That as her Rule hath Raignd twiſe <hi>Lev'n</hi> &amp; <hi>Sev'n</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>So may ſhee ſtill, ſurpas all Potent Peeres,</l>
                     <l>To liue, and long time wield the Ciuile ſwoord,</l>
                     <l>As far, as courſe of Nature can affoord.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:7"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Far <hi>Forrain lands,</hi> beare witneſſe of her <hi>Name;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Far <hi>ſurging Seas,</hi> haue felt her warlik Ships;</l>
                     <l>Both <hi>Seas,</hi> &amp; <hi>Lands,</hi> foorth thunder out her <hi>Fame,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Pama ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>net facti po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſito velami<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne, currunt: Et memore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Famam, qui bene geſsit habet. Ouid. lib. Faſt.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Through force of flowring Acts, free from Ecclips:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Elizabeths</hi> due praiſe ſhall neuer dye,</l>
                     <l>In <hi>Earth,</hi> nor <hi>Seas,</hi> nor in the <hi>ſtarry Skye.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Right <hi>Rev'rend Princeſſe,</hi> rare is thy Renown,</l>
                     <l>Though <hi>Spitefull Enuie,</hi> ſpue foorth poyſned gall;</l>
                     <l>Naught ſhall it craſe, thine Acts <hi>Eternall Crown,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Nor miniſh much, thy ſound ſucceſſe at all:</l>
                     <l>No <hi>BEST</hi> may ſhunne fell Enuies ſowrfull ſtench,<note n="*" place="margin">Arsprim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Regni, eſt poſſe Inuidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am pati. Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nec. in Herc. fur.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhom <hi>Kezars, Kings,</hi> &amp; <hi>Queenes,</hi> haue faild to quench.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>As Higheſt Hils, bide fierceſt force of VVeather,</l>
                     <l>And Tall Trees tops, beare greateſt ſtreſſe of VVinde,</l>
                     <l>As fineſt Black, yeelds ſhowe of ſmalleſt feather,</l>
                     <l>And in pure White, the leaſt black Mote wee finde:</l>
                     <l>So <hi>Envies</hi> ſhaft, is ſhot at<note n="*" place="margin">Su<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ma pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tit liuor, perflant al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſsima venti. Ouid.</note> 
                        <hi>Higheſt Mark;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And pries in <hi>Pureſt Things,</hi> whereat to bark.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:8"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No <hi>Ruler Such</hi> hath weld this Realme of yore,</l>
                     <l>Fewe Realmes haue ioy'd, ſo long a<note n="*" place="margin">Iniqua nunquam regna, per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuò ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent. <hi>Sen. in Med.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>Peacefull Rule:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>No Realme is read, t'haue Rul'de bin heretofore,</l>
                     <l>By ſuch a <hi>Queene,</hi> ſafe quelling Ciuile Brule;</l>
                     <l>Who raigning ſtill, a Prince withouten peere;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Her highnes</hi> now, holds on her <hi>Thirtieth yeere.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Adore <hi>Nouembers</hi> ſacred<note n="*" place="margin">More fit to be ſolemni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zed, then many other daies noted in the Ka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder.</note> 
                        <hi>Sev'nteenth Day,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wherein our <hi>Second Sunne</hi> began her Shine:</l>
                     <l>Ring out lowd ſounding Bels; on Organs play;</l>
                     <l>To Muſiks Mirth, let all Eſtates incline:</l>
                     <l>Sound Dru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mes, &amp; Tru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pets, renting Ayre &amp; Grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d</l>
                     <l>Stringd Jnstruments, ſtrike with Melodious ſound.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yee Mighty Men of <hi>Mars</hi> ennobled <hi>Knights,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Aduaunce your ſelues, on fiery foming ſteedes:</l>
                     <l>Reuiue <hi>This Times</hi> Remembrance, with all Rights,</l>
                     <l>Jn Armour bright, and gorgeous warlik weedes:</l>
                     <l>At <hi>Tylt,</hi> &amp; <hi>Turnay,</hi> trying Martiall Might;</l>
                     <l>And Battring ſtrokes, at <hi>Barriers</hi> forcefull fight.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:8"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yee Country folke, foorth ſtalking in your feeldes,</l>
                     <l>Lowd Carols ſing, to celebrate This Tyme;</l>
                     <l>Show Signes of ioy (as Country manner yeeldes,)</l>
                     <l>Jn Sporting Games, with Daunce, and rurall Ryme:</l>
                     <l>Eche Swayne, and Shepheard, ſou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d his piping Reede,</l>
                     <l>For ioy, enioying <hi>Feelds,</hi> &amp; <hi>Flocks</hi> to feede.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Yee <hi>Bryttiſh Poets,</hi> Repeate in Royall Song,</l>
                     <l>(With waighty woords, vſde in King <hi>Arthurs</hi> daies)</l>
                     <l>Th'<hi>Imperiall Stock,</hi> from whence your <hi>Queene</hi> hath ſprong</l>
                     <l>Enstall in verſe your <hi>Princeſſe</hi> lasting praies:</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Maiſters in the Science of Muſick.</note> 
                        <hi>Pencerddiaid,</hi> play on Auncient Harp, and Crowd:</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Expert men in ſinging.</note>
                        <hi>Atceiniaid,</hi> ſing her praiſes pearcing lowd.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Let Hilles, and Rocks, rebounding <hi>Ecchoes</hi> yeeld,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Queene Elizabeths</hi> long laſting Fame;</l>
                     <l>Let woody Groaues, and VVatry Streames be fild,</l>
                     <l>And Creekes, and Caues, with ſounding of the ſame:</l>
                     <l>O <hi>Cambria,</hi> ſtretch, and ſtraine thy vtmost breth,</l>
                     <l>To praiſe, and pray for <hi>Queene Elyzabeth.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:9"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her <hi>Third time Ten yeeres Raign,</hi> we now poſſeſſe;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Let euery faithfull ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iect ſay, Amen.</note>Thriſe three times Ten, <hi>God</hi> grau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t hir <hi>Grace</hi> may raign</l>
                     <l>To this her Realmes long wiſht for wealfulneſſe,</l>
                     <l>VVhereby, eche long erst Loſſe, it may Regain:</l>
                     <l>And ſo Redound, the happieſt Realme for ay,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nturn'd from <hi>Truth,</hi> ev'n till the <hi>Latter Day.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <closer>God preſerue Queene Elizabeth.</closer>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:9"/>
                  <p>ILLVSTRISSIMO CLARISSIMOQVE D. ROBERTO D'EVREVX, COMITI ESSEXIAE ET EWIAE, VICECOMITI HERE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FORDIAE AC BOVRCHIER, DO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MINO DE FERRARIIS DE CHARTLEIGH, BOVRCHI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ER ET LOVAIN.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>GEORGIANI ORDINIS EQVITI AVRATO ALIISQVE MVLTIS NOMINIBVS HONORATISSI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MO VIRO:</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>MAVRICIVS KYFFINVS ACCES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SIONEM HANC SVI LIBRI FOE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>LICITATIS BRYTANIAE, HO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NORIS SVMMAEQVE OB<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SERVANTIAE ERGO DEDICAT.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="illustration">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:10"/>
                  <p>
                     <figure>
                        <figDesc>blazon or coat of arms</figDesc>
                        <p>HONI SOIT QVI MAL Y PENSE</p>
                        <p>SEMPER EADEM</p>
                     </figure>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:10"/>
                  <head>
                     <hi>A CONTINVATION OF the Bleſſednes of Brytain, Comprehen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding</hi> the Thirtieth yeere of her Maieſties Raigne. 1588.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>MOst ſacred <hi>Muſes,</hi> lend me of your light,</l>
                     <l>To driue foorth darknes from my dull conceat:</l>
                     <l>Jmpart your Powrs, to ſharp my dimned ſight,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>perfect things,</hi> by pen I may repeat;</l>
                     <l>To honour <hi>her,</hi> with yeerely <hi>Fames</hi> encreaſe,</l>
                     <l>Who houlds the Helm, of our long laſting<note n="*" place="margin">Iuſtitia Regis, Pax eſt Populo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum. Cypr.</note> Peace.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Who Rules by <hi>Right,</hi> and liues in <hi>loue</hi> of all:<note place="margin">Iuſtitia fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>matur ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lium. <hi>Pro. 16.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Who wiſely works the <hi>Sauegard</hi> of her <hi>Land:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho both <hi>preuides,</hi> and eke <hi>preuents</hi> our fall:</l>
                     <l>Who gards, and guydes, her Realms fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Hoſtile hand:</l>
                     <l>Who hath the<note n="*" place="margin">Inexpug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nabile mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nimentum, Amor Giui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Seneca.</note> 
                        <hi>harts,</hi> of her leege folk in hold:</l>
                     <l>And whome <hi>Iehoue,</hi> hath bleſt ten Thouſand fold.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:11"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Such is our Sacred <hi>Sov'raigne,</hi> and our <hi>Queene:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such is her <hi>Care,</hi> to ſhield her Subiects ſtill:</l>
                     <l>Such be their <hi>Faithfull Harts,</hi> to herwards ſeene;</l>
                     <l>Such are the <hi>guifts,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tuta eſt Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditio ſubie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vbi vi uitur ſub Aequitate Regna<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tium. <hi>Caſs. li. 3. Ep.</hi>
                        </note> of <hi>Gods</hi> moſt <hi>gracious will:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such is the Life we lead with her in <hi>bliſſe;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Such is the <hi>Queene</hi> we may by no meanes miſſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Adore we <hi>God</hi> who lends vs ſtill her lyfe:</l>
                     <l>Adore we <hi>her,</hi> whom <hi>God</hi> hath plas'd in Powre:</l>
                     <l>Adore we <hi>him</hi> in <hi>her</hi> that Stints our Strife:</l>
                     <l>Adore we <hi>Both,</hi> Reſpectiuelie, eche howre:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>one</hi> in Heav'n Directs vs by his Grace:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>other</hi> here on Earth, ſupplieth his place.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Time was</hi> whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                        <hi>Popes</hi> through-pold this Royal Ream,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Plato aſse<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, Tyrannt de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſſe, cum vi compulſi Ciue<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> Iugu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſeruitutis violenter ſubeunt: Reg<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                        </note>Reauing eche <hi>Right,</hi> fowle <hi>Might</hi> Miſruling all:</l>
                     <l>And as ſtearn Rage of ſtrong and ſturdy ſtream,</l>
                     <l>Down-bearing Banks and Bridges forst to fall;</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo by <hi>will</hi> they wrought the Peoples wrack,</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Luſt</hi> was their Law, the Ruefull land to Rack.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:11"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Time is,</hi> when <hi>Iuſtice</hi> houlds the <hi>Regall Throne;</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Regnu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> au<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, cum vltro pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t pare<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                           <expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Dime<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Iuſtitiae &amp; Officioru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expectant. <hi>Fr. patr. De Regno &amp; Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gis inſtitutio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ne.</hi> Firmabitur Iustitia Thronus. <hi>Pro. 15.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>From whence as from a ſure, and ſacred Spring,</l>
                     <l>Furth flowes the flood of <hi>Royal Right</hi> alone,</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hich maſtreth <hi>Might,</hi> and ſtill withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds his ſting:</l>
                     <l>Compare <hi>Times paſt</hi> with this our <hi>preſent Age:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVe Rul'd by <hi>Right:</hi> They, wro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>gd by <hi>Cruel Rage.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Time ſhalbe,</hi> when our murding Malecontents,<note place="margin">Qui contra ſuprapoſita<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi poteſtate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> murmurat: Liquet quòd illum redar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guit qui ea<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Homini potestatem dedit. <hi>Greg. in Mor.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hich Murmur, and Malign this ſhining <hi>State;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Shall, to their Shame, acknow with full Conſents,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Truth</hi> they tread in wrongfull harbourd hate:</l>
                     <l>Then ſhall appeere, in playne and publick ſight,</l>
                     <l>The diffrent works of <hi>wrong</hi> and eke of <hi>Right.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Nullatam modesta foe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licitas eſt vt Malignita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis de<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tes vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tare poſsit. Senec.</note>Some muddy Mindes no <hi>Cleernes</hi> can content,</l>
                     <l>But euer thickning thirſt for Troubled Change:</l>
                     <l>Hanging their Hopes on <hi>future</hi> falſe <hi>euent,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhereby they ſeek ſome Alteration ſtrange:</l>
                     <l>
                        <note n="*" place="margin">Huiuſmo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Artes nu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gatoriae vel noxiae Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlitionis ex quada<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fera ſocieta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>te hominum &amp; Demonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtituta, pe nitus ſunt Repudiandae &amp; ſugienda Chriſtiano. Aug.</note>Others do Calk, and caſt <hi>Conſtellations;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>And yet be deceyv'd by deepe <hi>Diuinations.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:12"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The fatall yeere of fearefull <hi>Eighty Eight,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Forethreatning falls of <hi>Empires, Realms,</hi> &amp; <hi>Kings:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Out-breathing Bale, to euery Earthly wight,</l>
                     <l>By peſtring Plagues, and Dreadfull drery things:</l>
                     <l>Is Now nigh ſpent, and yet our <hi>Realm</hi> &amp; <hi>Queene,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Through <hi>Gods great Pow'r,</hi> ſecure in Saftie ſeene.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Whereby appeeres, <hi>Mens</hi> propheſies be vaine,</l>
                     <l>When <hi>God</hi> decreeth a Contrarie Succeſſe:<note place="margin">That which the Lord of Hoſts hath d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>termined, who is able reſiſt? Eſay. 14.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Fraud</hi> is the frute of <hi>Mans</hi> vnſtable braine</l>
                     <l>Out-ſtrayd from <hi>Truth,</hi> in <hi>Errors</hi> wide exceſſe:</l>
                     <l>Who truſts <hi>Vntroth</hi> muſt needs downſlip and ſlide:</l>
                     <l>Men are but Men, <hi>God</hi> is the certaine <hi>Guide.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>This was the yeere, wherein by <hi>Fire</hi> and <hi>Sword,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our Foes forethought, to woork this Kingdoms wrack:</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Accipe nunc Dan<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>um Inſidias &amp; crimine ab vno. Diſce omnes.</note>Againſt which <hi>Time,</hi> much Malice hid in hoord,</l>
                     <l>And now deſcride, diſcovreth all their Pack:</l>
                     <l>Long erſt were laide foregrounds for our Regreete</l>
                     <l>Ere Fame was furth iſprad of <hi>Spaniſh fleete.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:12"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>VVhich hugie <hi>Fleete,</hi> full fraught with <hi>Murdring Mindes</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Such a fleet, as the like was neuer known or read of be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</note>Meaning <hi>Maſſacre</hi> to our <hi>Natiue Soyle:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Being furniſht furth with Ships of ſundry kindes,</l>
                     <l>To geue the <hi>Fall:</hi> Receiv'd them ſelues the <hi>Foyle:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Prays be <hi>His</hi> who ſtill protects our Cauſe:</l>
                     <l>Foulding his <hi>Flock</hi> from Rauening Wooluiſh Iawes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Strange was the Stroke wherewith they went to wrack,</l>
                     <l>On diuers Coaſts of Countries round about:<note place="margin">God ſcatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices of the Craſty: So that their hands ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not accompliſh that which they doe en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terpriſe. Iob. 5.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Before which <hi>Fall,</hi> their Liues ſuſteind much <hi>lack,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Of Needfull things, vnable to hould out:</l>
                     <l>Then <hi>drery Drowning,</hi> ſtopt their ſtaruen breath,</l>
                     <l>By <hi>heapes of hundreds</hi> haald to dole full Death.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A <hi>Miracle of mightie Magnitude,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Don by the Dreadfull Powre of <hi>Gods</hi> Right hand:<note place="margin">This was the Lords doing, And it is marueilous in our eyes. Pſal. 118.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>herein our <hi>Might</hi> and Meanes he did exclude,</l>
                     <l>That ſo himſelf <hi>moſt Gloriouſly</hi> may ſtand:</l>
                     <l>Jt is beyond the Reache of Humane thought,</l>
                     <l>To think the <hi>Things</hi> he for our ſakes hath wrought.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:13"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>By hideous ſtormes, their Ships conſtraynd to ſtray,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">The Times whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: The pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces where: And the ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner how: Is particularly declared in the late Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uertiſments thereof ſent from Ireland.</note>Ruſht ſome on Rocks, and ſome on Sholles and Sands,</l>
                     <l>Betottred, torn, and Rent in Wrackt array:</l>
                     <l>Much of their <hi>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, dead</hi> ſtrowd on Shoares &amp; Stra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ds:</l>
                     <l>Others Deuourd in Depth of Surging Seas,</l>
                     <l>Both <hi>Men</hi> and <hi>Ships,</hi> the waters wrath t'appeas.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>So <hi>Pharaos</hi> hoaſt was drencht in Drowning fluds,</l>
                     <l>As he purſude poore <hi>Iſrael</hi> folk amayne,</l>
                     <l>From <hi>Pharaos</hi> ſtock, furth bloamd theſe <hi>balefull buds,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Which in like ſort, for like Attempt are ſlayne.</l>
                     <l>Fierce <hi>Pharao</hi> found <hi>Due guerdon</hi> for his guylt:</l>
                     <l>The like <hi>Due Doome,</hi> their <hi>Spaniſh Pomp</hi> hath ſpilt.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The furious Foe enthralld in thirſt of Blood,</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Furor Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinguibilis, quem Regni furioſa Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pido accen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dit.</note>Whos Rauenous Rore, outreacheth <hi>Seas</hi> and <hi>Lands,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Still Raging, ſeeks Subuerſion of the <hi>Good,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>By Mighty Meanes of ſtearnfull Armed Bands:</l>
                     <l>But <hi>God</hi> Regarding his true Peoples plight;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Preue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts</hi> their <hi>wrong,</hi> &amp; makes <hi>preuail</hi> their <hi>Right</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:13"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No <hi>Councels,</hi> or <hi>Complots of Men,</hi> may ſtand:</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Stratagems,</hi> of ſtrange inuented Jll:</l>
                     <l>Or <hi>Strength by Sea,</hi> or <hi>Puiſſant Powre</hi> by Land,</l>
                     <l>To ſtriue with <hi>God,</hi> or ſtraine beyond his <hi>will.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God</hi> fights for vs, &amp; ſhields our Liues from <hi>Thrall:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">If God bee with vs, who can be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs? Paul. 8. Rom.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhat skills it than, who be our <hi>Foes</hi> at all?</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>The <hi>Proſprous plight,</hi> and <hi>Peace</hi> of this our Land:<note place="margin">Acrius Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitibus qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Pauperibus inuidetur: &amp; non In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>opes, ſed Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cupletes, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quietat In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſtatio ſae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua Latro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>num. Aug.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>(A heauy hart-ſore to our Fuming foes)</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>p-mooues their <hi>Mindes,</hi> with grudging to gainſtand:</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>iſhing our <hi>weale,</hi> were turnd to <hi>wailing woes.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Bronds of <hi>Enuie,</hi> burn ſo in their breſt,</l>
                     <l>As ſtill they Rage to <hi>Reaue our Liues</hi> of Rest.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Fowl <hi>Tyrannie,</hi> purſues with pearcing hate,</l>
                     <l>Such as abhorre the Cruell ſhead of blood:</l>
                     <l>For herein cheefly ſtands the <hi>Tyran ſtate,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Tyrannus infenſus eſt Omnibus qui Virtuti ſtudent. Fr. Patr. de Reg. &amp;c.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>To ſhrowd the <hi>Bad,</hi> and ſeeke to ſhread the <hi>Good.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Lo here the <hi>ſink</hi> of <hi>Machiauels</hi> lewd Lore;</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>here Tyrants turn them ſelues to <hi>bloody gore.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Wo woorth the wretch that wrote thoſe <hi>Rules</hi> of <hi>Rage:</hi>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>N. Machiauel las Flore<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t. per nicioſiſſ. Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor: qui in ſuo Libro de principe nihil fere tradidit praeter Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: nidis inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>endae Prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepta: quoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> pauca ſunt hac. viz.</hi> Principe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Sae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uitiae fama<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> negligere debere. Vtilius eſſe Principt metui qua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> amari. Crudelitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qua laudabi lem fine<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſibi propon<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>t, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>di non deberi. Principem Peierare, Fallere, &amp; Diſsimulare ſine vlla du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitatione li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere. Principem prudente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dem ſeruare non debere, ſi da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>no ei eſt Fidem, Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tiam, Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>beralitatem Virtutes eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſe damnoſas principi.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wo woorth the <hi>Peeres,</hi> which practiſe them in life:</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ile <hi>Machiauell,</hi> thy pen depaints <hi>Outrage,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>To plunge a <hi>Prince,</hi> in ſtreames of <hi>bloody ſtrife,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>The Feends infernall, fraught thy Reaching brain</l>
                     <l>With wiles to work thy Follwers endles Payn.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Thoſe be our Foes, whom <hi>Machiauel</hi> hath ſchoold;</l>
                     <l>With whom are ioynd, fals <hi>Iudas</hi> faith-lorn <hi>Crew:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But <hi>Ioue the iuſt Iudge,</hi> their courage hath coold,</l>
                     <l>Who made them drink the Draught they for vs drew.</l>
                     <l>Thus <hi>Tyra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nie,</hi> and <hi>Treaſon,</hi> Trauaild with hate,</l>
                     <l>To <hi>ſeege</hi> and <hi>ſubuert</hi> this <hi>Peacefull Eſtate.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And Trans-pakt Traytors, bragging made their boast,</l>
                     <l>Of <hi>Lands,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Magis Inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dijs noſtroru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> quam Alio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum pericli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tamur. Iſid. Caueamus igitur perfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum, Caue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amus Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap>orem. Ambr.</note> and <hi>Lordſhips,</hi> here to hould by <hi>Spoyl:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>But as they Reckend wyde without their Oaſt,</l>
                     <l>So muſt they trye much <hi>Terror,</hi> Teene, and Toyle,</l>
                     <l>And looſe their Liues, (Defilde with fowle Defect)</l>
                     <l>Ere that their VVreakfull Willes do work effect.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:14"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Hi trifor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mes Canes ora proter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ua habent intonancia ingenti La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tratu.</note>Theſe are the Treble <hi>Treaſon-headed</hi> whelps:</l>
                     <l>Their ſire is <hi>Cerberus</hi> huge hound of Hell;</l>
                     <l>Whos <hi>threefold throat,</hi> ſtill yeelds the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> yallping helps,</l>
                     <l>To Bark, and Bawle, with hideous ſounding yell,<note place="margin">Treble, Traitors. viz. To God: To their Prince: To their Country.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>Gainſt <hi>God,</hi> their <hi>Prince,</hi> and <hi>Cuntry,</hi> at a breath:</l>
                     <l>Truſting by <hi>Treaſon,</hi> to ſee <hi>True mens</hi> death.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>All <hi>Faithfull Subiects,</hi> ſerue your <hi>Royall Queene,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Nemo enim Bello laceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſere aut fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cere audet Iniuriam Regno vel populo, que<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> expeditu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; promptu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ad reſiſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dum vindican<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dum<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>noſcit. <hi>Veg. lib. 4. cap. 13.</hi>
                        </note>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVith wonted Might, and Magnitude of Harts:</l>
                     <l>Such let your powr, and Puiſſance be ſeene,</l>
                     <l>As may forefaint your <hi>Foes</hi> with griſlie ſmarts:</l>
                     <l>Euen ſo beſits it woorthy warlik wights,</l>
                     <l>To Fight in Fe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of <hi>Queene</hi> and <hi>Cuntry Rights.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho will not Fight againſt a <hi>Cruell Foe?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>How can we Ioyne <hi>in Iuſter Cauſe</hi> of fight?</l>
                     <l>Than to Conſerue our ſelues from <hi>ſlaughtring woe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ith Courage fierce, and forcefull Manly Might?</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Lands Liberties,</hi> and <hi>Liues,</hi> lye on the ſtake;</l>
                     <l>VVhereof eche priuate perſon dooth partake.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:15"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>For wicked Machiauel ſaith:</hi> Principe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in Prouincia nuper victa, oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s quibus mutatio gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ui damno eſt ſubuertere debere: At<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> eoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> qui pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>us in ea do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minaban<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>am ac ſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem ab ſtirpe tollere.</note>VVhere <hi>Tyrants</hi> triumph, Miſcheefs muſt enſue:</l>
                     <l>No ſpare of <hi>hoary Age,</hi> or <hi>Infants</hi> ſmall:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Matrons,</hi> &amp; <hi>Mayds,</hi> their ſhameful Rape ſhal Rue:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Slaughter</hi> and <hi>Slav'ry,</hi> ſhalbe ſervd on all:</l>
                     <l>Huge Stormes, &amp; ſtreames, of waſtful wrack &amp; woe,</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Cities, Townes,</hi> and <hi>Fields,</hi> ſhall ouer-floe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>And againe:</hi> Principem ſi quidin Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gione falſi eſt, Id co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mare debere</note>Beſides their <hi>Rage,</hi> and <hi>Rancour,</hi> raught at full,</l>
                     <l>On <hi>Lim,</hi> &amp; <hi>Life,</hi> where loſſe hath wrought their gaine;</l>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">
                           <hi>And in ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther place preferring the Pagans Religion be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore Chriſts, he ſaith:</hi> Religionem Ethnicorum Animos illis excelſos &amp; ad magnas res fortiterſuſcipiendas audaces feciſſe: Chriſtianoru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> verò Religione<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> mentes in ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miam humilitate<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> deprimere: Indole<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> oe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>m debilitare, eoſ<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> Iniuriae ac praedae opportunos facere.</note>The Pillers pure of <hi>faith,</hi> they will down pull,</l>
                     <l>Tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pling <hi>Chriſts truth,</hi> with mo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtrous might &amp; main</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Rightfull Religion,</hi> ſhall to <hi>Ruin</hi> Ronne;</l>
                     <l>Gainſt which, no fowle <hi>Deſpite</hi> ſhall faile vndonne.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Theſe be the <hi>Things,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Diu adpa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dum eſt Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lum vt vin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cas celerius: quia longa belli praepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ratio celere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> facit Victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riam. <hi>Sen. in Epi. 15</hi>
                        </note> our Enimies forethreat:</l>
                     <l>Theſe be the <hi>frutes,</hi> and <hi>furies</hi> of our foes:</l>
                     <l>Theſe be the <hi>Men,</hi> we muſt in <hi>Time</hi> back-beat.</l>
                     <l>Theſe be the <hi>Clouds,</hi> whence all fowle weather growes:</l>
                     <l>Then Arme,<note place="margin">Plurimu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. n. Terroris Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtibus Armo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> Splendor importat. <hi>Veg. lib. 2.</hi>
                        </note> with Alarm, their ſlights we do ſee:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Once warnd, Euer Armd,</hi> henceforth we ſhould bee.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:15"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>For though their <hi>Late Attempt</hi> Returnd them <hi>Loſſe,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Whereas they weend to <hi>winne</hi> and wreak their hate,<note place="margin">Mala Ment, Malus Ani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mus.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>And thereby ſore ſuſteind a <hi>Deadly Croſſe:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Yet doth their <hi>murdring Malice,</hi> naught abate;</l>
                     <l>But will <hi>Retrye</hi> their Trechrous <hi>Miſcheefs</hi> ment;</l>
                     <l>VVhom to <hi>Reſiſt</hi> we muſt be <hi>Ready</hi> bent.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Conioyne all in ſtrength of hearts, and ſtrong hands;<note place="margin">Quum te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                           <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pus Neceſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tas<expan>
                              <am>
                                 <g ref="char:abque"/>
                              </am>
                              <ex>que</ex>
                           </expan> poſtu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lat, decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tandum. est manu, &amp; Mors Serui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuti Turpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tudinique antepone<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>da. Cicero. Donabit Certanti Victoriam qui certan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di dedit Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>daciam, Aug.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>As <hi>warriours</hi> and <hi>wreakers,</hi> of <hi>vnbrooked wrongs:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>In Ire, all on fire, like wilde burning brands;</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>Skattring,</hi> and <hi>battring,</hi> our <hi>foes</hi> thickeſt throngs:</l>
                     <l>
                        <hi>God</hi> will furth guyde vs with <hi>victorie</hi> and <hi>Fame:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Downfelling our <hi>foes</hi> with <hi>Infamy</hi> and <hi>ſhame.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>And thank we highly<note n="*" place="margin">In ſomuch as God hath deliuered vs from great perrills, wee thank him highly. 2. Mackab. 1.11.</note> 
                        <hi>Him</hi> that held vs vp,</l>
                     <l>From plunging <hi>Pits,</hi> of griſlie <hi>Perrils paſt,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhere others ſank, and (ſorrows forſt to ſup)</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ith huge conſuming Cares were ouercaſt:</l>
                     <l>Our Neereſt <hi>Neighbours,</hi> neuer Ioyd the<note n="*" place="margin">Tale Bonu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> eſt bonum Pacis vt in rebus crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tis nil gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioſius ſole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>at audiri: nil delecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſci: &amp; ni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hil vtilius poſsidert. Aug. d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                              <desc>•••</desc>
                           </gap>iu. Det.</note> 
                        <hi>Reſt</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>VVhich we <hi>whole Thirtie yeeres</hi> haue here poſſest.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:16"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>No, nor this <hi>Land,</hi> had euer earſt the like,</l>
                     <l>In all the Princes dayes that Rulde the ſame:</l>
                     <l>But often goard with Puſh of warring Pike,</l>
                     <l>It bare the brunt of <hi>Famin, Sword,</hi> and <hi>Flame:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Saue in our <hi>Queenes,</hi> bright ſhyning Days of Peace,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>Heav'nly health,</hi> and <hi>worldly welth</hi> increaſe.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <note place="margin">Vaeduplici corde ſuo, partem fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciunt Deo, &amp; partem Diabolo. Aug.</note>VVho than can Doubt, or deeme in Double Harte,</l>
                     <l>But <hi>God</hi> hath wroght great <hi>wonders</hi> by our <hi>Queene?</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hereof (All partiall Cenſures, put a parte:)</l>
                     <l>Abundant <hi>Proofs</hi> and <hi>Precedents</hi> be ſeene.</l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>hereon, a ſure <hi>Concluſion</hi> ſound doth ſort,</l>
                     <l>That <hi>God</hi> will ſtill her <hi>Royall State</hi> ſupport.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Full <hi>Thirty yeeres her Gouernment hath dur'de;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Wherby what precious Frutes her Realmes haue reapt</l>
                     <l>All Subiects in their Conſcience are aſſur'de,</l>
                     <l>On whom the goulden grayn thereof is heapt:</l>
                     <l>The <hi>Eternall God</hi> prolong her <hi>Ruling dayes,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>His <hi>Glorious Name,</hi> to further furth alwayes.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:16"/>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Powre Prayres, and Prayſes, to the <hi>King of Kings,</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ho makes the <hi>world</hi> a witnes of our <hi>weale,</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Who ſo offe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>
                           <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>reth me prays and thanks, hee honoreth me. Pſalm. 50.</note>
                     </l>
                     <l>By <hi>perfect Peace,</hi> and <hi>Plenty</hi> of all things:</l>
                     <l>VVhoſe guift it is, our <hi>Foes</hi> to <hi>fore-reueale.</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Els <hi>Lack, War,</hi> &amp; <hi>wrack,</hi> wold work al our <hi>woes:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>Our <hi>Liues, Lands,</hi> &amp; <hi>wiues</hi> ſubiected to <hi>Foes.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Her <hi>Highnes One</hi> and <hi>Thirtieth yeere</hi> ſucceedes,</l>
                     <l>Renewing Now, Nouembers <hi>Sev'nteenth day:</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>On which, ſhe firſt tyme ware th' <hi>Imperiall weedes;</hi>
                     </l>
                     <l>A <hi>Royall making</hi> to this <hi>Realme</hi> alway.</l>
                     <l>Long may Her <hi>Grace</hi> Renew her Raigning yeeres:</l>
                     <l>And Lyue a Patern to all <hi>Princely Peeres.</hi>
                     </l>
                  </lg>
                  <epigraph>
                     <q>
                        <bibl>
                           <hi>Pſalm. 147.</hi>
                        </bibl>
                        <p>
                           <hi>O</hi> Hieruſalem praiſe the Lord: Praiſe thy God, o Sion. For he hath ſtrengthned the Barres of thy Gates: And hath bleſſed thy Children within thee. Hee hath made all thy Borders Peace: And with the good Nutriment of VVheate doth ſatisfie thee, &amp;c. Hee hath not don thus to euery Nation els: Praiſe wee all the Lord therefore. Amen.</p>
                     </q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               </div>
               <div xml:lang="fre" type="poem">
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:17"/>
                  <head>A Monſieur M. Kyffin Poëte: Sonet.</head>
                  <lg>
                     <l>
                        <hi>O</hi> Que ie te connois, Poëte digne d'vn Laurier,</l>
                     <l>Gentil Kyffin, chantre d'vn Heröique vers</l>
                     <l>Figuré, court, limé, rich en langage diuers</l>
                     <l>Pour le parler Anglois, Poëte bon-ouurier.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Ta Muſe eſt arriueé à vn auguſt port,</l>
                     <l>La ſacreé Deeſs', à la Royalle Grace,</l>
                     <l>Fille d'vn Sire-Souuerain, la prudente Pallas,</l>
                     <l>ELIZABETH la Grande, Claire Perle du Nort.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Princeſſe redoutée de toute la Machine ronde,</l>
                     <l>Aiant pour ſon Guidon le plus grand Roy des Rois</l>
                     <l>De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>fiers Heſpaignols rembarre lesfiers arrois,</l>
                     <l>Et combatte, guerriere, leur Armée vagabonde.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>A beaux coups de Cannons l'enfonce, force au naufrage,</l>
                     <l>Fend l'Ost Heſpaignol &amp; le prent en pillage</l>
                     <l>Par ſon Armée Royalle, voyant que tel bagage</l>
                     <l>N'estoit vogué ſur mer ſinon en brigandage.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>O que c'est vn grand heur de viure ſous tel Prince.</l>
                     <l>Heureux, Anglois heureux viuant où droit &amp; Loy</l>
                     <l>Venerable fleurit auec la blanche Foy</l>
                     <l>Sous la Royne Paiſible, qui gouuerne ta Prouince.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Hola ma Muſe, tay-toy. Kyffin a bien chanté</l>
                     <l>De ſa Iuſtice, Bonté, Prudence &amp; pieté</l>
                     <l>Et ſes autres vertus, dont il fait vn meſlange,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Donc mon gentil Kyffin Poëte braue en ton langage.</l>
                     <l>Sois premier en honneur, bien que dernier en age,</l>
                     <l>Encor tu chanteras maint annees ſa louange,</l>
                  </lg>
                  <lg>
                     <l>Seruant d'vn Virgil à celle qui promet rendre</l>
                     <l>Egaux ſes Laurien, aux Lauriers d' Alexandre,</l>
                     <l>ELIZABETH la Grande, terrestre Royne &amp; Ange.</l>
                  </lg>
                  <trailer>VIVE LA ROYNE ELIZABETH.</trailer>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>I. Eliote.</signed>
                  </closer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:8603:17"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
